很久以前 音乐库里还没有迪士尼版权的时候……
星
船
第15号
*一次新的跳跃*
这是一段持续测试的时代
SpaceX的一些Starship从一个远程基地起飞
对*重力*获得了一些微小的胜利
在飞行过程中SpaceX工程师们从他们的秘密武器上获得了关键的飞行数据
他们的秘密武器就是*猛禽发动机* 一台全流量分级燃烧循环的火箭发动机
能抬起一整座粮仓
业余储罐观察者观察到 马一龙回到了德克萨斯州
保管着美国国家航空航天局提供的合同 而这将支持这个项目
并发展出前往太空的低成本技术……
原视频名：SpaceX's Starship Prototype Takes To The Skies And Returns Safely
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/7IDMM63InLY
原视频发布日期：20210506
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello, it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
What a marvelous intro that was.
那是一个多么了不起的开场啊
Yeah, I put that together as a joke,
是的 为了搞笑 我把它放在一起
because there was a good chance that Starship Serial Number 15 was going to fly on May the fourth,
因为编号为15的星船原本很有可能会在5月4日飞行
but you know what It still works,
但你猜怎么着 这个笑话仍然有效
because we can call that revenge of the 5th.
因为我们可以称其为5号的复仇
Like, regardless, yes,
就像……不管这些了 是的
SpaceX yesterday, they successfully flew a Starship for a High altitude test.
SpaceX昨天 成功地让一艘星船进行了高空试飞
They performed their belly flop.
进行了腹部向下机动
They performed their transition to landing, and they landed,
进行了着陆前的姿态转变 并且着陆了
and they didn't explode 10 minutes later
而且10分钟后也没有爆炸
marking the first fully successful flight of a Starship prototype, showing the whole system.
这标志着星船原型机的首次完全成功飞行 验证了整个系统
Now this is a pretty big deal because we've seen four failures so far.
那么这是很重要的 因为到目前为止已经发生了四次失败
Because of the way SpaceX is very happy to throw hardware out there and test it by flying it.
因为SpaceX非常乐意把设备放在外边 并通过飞行来测试它
But SN15 had a number of changes that were expected to solve problems that had previously been seen.
但SN15有一些变化 之前就预计能解决以前看到的问题
So the first set of prototypes that had flown this high altitude flight, were the SN 8, 9, 10 and 11.
因此 第一组曾进行高海拔试飞的原型机是SN8 9 10和11
And they had failed because of design problems with the Starship hardware,
而他们失败的原因是星船设备的设计问题
and also with design problems or fabrication problems with the Raptor engines.
还有则是猛禽发动机的设计或制造问题
And both of those had received revisions for SN15,
而这两部分在SN15上都得到了改进
and by the way, 12 through 14 were never completed and were never intended to fly.
同时顺便说一下 12至14号从未完成或打算飞行
So 15 had new plumbing and changes,
那么15号有新的管道和其他的一些变化
I think it's inside the thrust pot,
我想这是在推力锅(推力穹顶)里面
but we're not too clear on exactly what changes happened,
但我们并不太清楚到底发生了什么变化
or at least if we have a few clues as to what might have changed,
或者至少知道一点点线索
but by no means an exhaustive list of things or why.
但绝不详尽 也没有原因
The Raptors were also redesigned and upgraded
猛禽也被重新设计并升级了
and boy, it looks like those combination of upgrades may have actually made it work,
而老兄啊 看起来这些升级的组合可能真的能起作用
although it wasn't 100% perfect.
尽管这并不是完美的
We did have problems here and there, and we'll talk about that.
待会我们会讨论这之中发生的一些问题
Now, the flight should have been absolutely spectacular, but we didn't see all of it,
那么 飞行绝对应该是壮观的 但我们并没有全部看到
because there was a cloud layer at about 1000 feet.
因为云层在大约300米处
So all those wonderful people who bring their cameras out to watch this spectacle,
那么 所有那些带着相机出来观看这一奇观的好人
they got to see this amazing launch.
都看到了这惊人的发射
You've got to see the vehicle lift slowly off the pad
你能看到航天器缓慢离开发射台
and then disappear into the cloud layer for several minutes,
然后在云层中消失数分钟
and then appeared back out from the clouds, rockets firing and landed safely.
然后又从云层中出现 火箭点火并安全着陆
And that was pretty good.
而那是相当好的
So anything above the clouds, we pretty much had to rely on SpaceX's on board cameras,
因此 任何在云上的景象都要依靠SpaceX的箭载相机来看
and it looked like they had made some effort to upgrade the quality.
而且看起来他们已经做了一些努力来提升质量
Their livestream was in 4K I notice.
我注意到他们的现场直播是4K分辨率的
And the camera that we were seeing from inside the skirt
而裙板里的相机
actually showed a lot more detail on the edges and on the Raptor.
实际上给裙板的边缘还有猛禽都展现了更多的细节
Things looked a lot better.
看起来好多了
But there were all sorts of problems with the signal,
但信号出现了各种问题
and the video kept on freezing for several minutes at a time.
而且视频每次都会冻结几分钟
We would sometimes get snippets of video
我们有时能看到一些视频片段
and then it would go away, or we might get just motion vectors, and the mush flying around.
然后就会消失 或者可能会看到发动机矢量的运动 以及烟雾的运动
And this meant that we did miss most of the flight.
这意味着我们确实错过了大部分的飞行过程
We did get to see that the engine shut off.
我们确实看到了发动机关闭的情况
But I think my favorite moment from the flight was
但在飞行中 我最喜欢的时刻是
they had now fitted a camera to one of the fins on the vehicle.
现在他们在航天器的一个翼面上安装了相机
And these fins, they move up and down to adjust the aerodynamic drag,
而这些翼面可以上下移动以调整空气阻力
and therefore adjust the horizontal orientation.
并以此调整水平姿态
So you got to see the horizon tilting as these fins moved.
所以你可以看到地平线随着这些翼面的移动而倾斜
But also, during one sequence, they were falling with their plume, right?
但同样地 在一段视频中 航天器落入了云雾 对吧
The cloud plume that they had made on the way up,
也就是其在上升过程中产生的云层
it was behind them, so we actually got to see this falling down past,
就在其身后 那么实际上我们看到了其从中坠落的过程
and it looked amazing at this all depth and quality to it that had never quite seen.
而且这样好的深度和质量是以前的影像中从未见过的
But yeah it seemed that the video quality might have been related to the fact
但是 是的 视频质量似乎与这些事情有关
that they were maybe testing delivering video over their Starlink network.
也许他们正在测试使用他们的Starlink网络来传输视频
So a few weeks ago,
那么几周前
SpaceX had applied to fly a Starlink antenna on the side of a Starship.
SpaceX已经申请在一艘星船的侧面安装一个Starlink天线 并在试飞中使用
And well, I mean, they were approved, you can actually see it on the side.
恩 我是指 这件事被批准了 实际上你可以在侧面看到它
I guess it didn't target so well, or there's problems still to be worked out.
我猜它的指向不是那么好 或者还有问题需要解决
During the flight, we also see IP addresses like you see udp://234.70.253.161:9000.
在飞行过程中 我们还看到了IP地址 比如udp://234.70.253.161:9000
That's like, UDP video streaming that they were pulling data from.
这差不多是 他们正在拉取的UDP视频流
And 234 address range,
而这个234的地址范围
I believe that's actually a public multicast address that might have been visible on the Internet,
我相信这实际上是一个公共组播地址 可能在互联网上可见
but I doubt it, like, just because it's a publicly routable address
但我怀疑 就因为它是一个可路由的地址
doesn't mean that it would actually be visible to the public. Let's say.
并不意味着它实际上是公开的 可以这么说
So I don't know.
那么我不清楚
By the way, we knew it was VLC, which is a open source media player,
顺便说一下 我们知道这是VLC 一个开源的媒体播放器
because the font pretty much matched what VLC uses, but I thought that was kind of cute.
因为其字体与VLC使用的字体几乎一致 但我认为这有点可爱
SpaceX just using what works right?
SpaceX就使用有效的东西 对吧
Now one important bit that we sort of glitched out a little was when the engines lit
那么有一个重要的部分 差点被忽略了 就是当发动机点燃的时候
John Insprucker是SpaceX的首席集成工程师，也是历次Starship SN系列试飞直播的主持人
because in previous flights and according to John Insprucker, the plan this time was to fire three engines,
因为在以前的飞行中 同时根据John Insprucker的说法 这次的计划是点燃三台发动机
and then downselect to two engines for orientation to the vertical.
然后选择两台发动机用于向垂直姿态的转变
And then switch to a single engine for the landing.
然后改用单台发动机进行着陆
But in this case, it looks like the only lit two engines.
但这次 似乎只点燃了两台发动机
It looks to me and most other people, the third engine immediately swung out of the way.
在我和其他大多数人看来 第三台发动机立刻摆开了
So it's not clear whether that one engine was voted out before it was even lit,
所以不清楚那台发动机是否在点火前就被淘汰了
whether it was ruled out due to something prior to ignition.
是否由于点火前的一些原因而被排除了
But I think that one would have been one of the first ones to ignite,
但我认为那台发动机应该是最先被点燃的发动机之一
because it's one of the engines, towards the belly of the vehicle,
因为它是朝向航天器腹部的发动机之一
and therefore actually provides slightly more lever arm.
因此实际上其力矩稍多
Because of the orientation of the fins,
因为翼面的指向
whereas the two that did light, or one of the ones that did light, didn't do that quite as well.
而那两台点燃的 或其中一台点燃的发动机 并不能做得一样好
So we had two engines were working, which wouldn't be the first choice of a pair of engines to land.
那么有两台在工作的发动机不是原定着陆要用的一对发动机
It also came in and down a lot faster.
它进入垂直姿态并下降的速度也快了很多
If you do look at pixel counts, compared to SN10 which was their successful landing,
如果你真的去数像素 与SN10 也就是之前的*成功*着陆相比
It was coming down faster and higher and breaking faster as well,
SN15下来的(初)速度更快 高度更高 减速度也更大
although it managed to throttle down and safely land.
尽管它成功地节流并安全着陆
Based on my pixel counts, it was moving at less than three meters per second, less than 10 feet per second,
根据我的像素计数 它的移动速度不到3m/s(10ft/s)
as opposed to SN10 which we know was about 10 meters per second or 33 feet per second
与SN10相比 我们知道它的速度大概是10m/s(33ft/s)
depending upon what your unit preference is.
这将取决于你的单位偏好
The landing wasn't totally clean by any means.
着陆并不完美
We can now see on the pad that there were black marks where the feet had hit,
我们现在可以在着陆场上看到 在着陆腿落地的地方有黑色的痕迹
and then they slid sideways a couple of feet.
然后还向侧面滑行了几米
Also. seems pretty close to the edge of the pad.
另外 着陆似乎非常接近着陆场的边缘
You can actually see, by the way, from the skirt camera.
顺便说一下 你实际上可以从裙板内的相机看到
As it comes down and performs this transition,
当它下来并执行这个过渡机动时
You get to see the the tank farm from high up.
可以从高处看到储罐场的情况
And then you get to see sections of the landing pad,
然后你就可以看到着陆场的各个部分
you can see in the background,
你可以在背景中看到
just the little of fire hose there
你可以看到一点消防水管
that was going to be needed for the post flight fire.
这些消防水管会被用于飞行后的消防工作
Yeah they landed and there was immediately lots of methane burning out the side.
是的 他们降落后 立即有很多甲烷从侧面燃烧起来
Wasn't clear how much of this was actually a leak,
不清楚这其中有多少是真的泄漏
or whether this was just stuff left open in the pipes.
或者只是管道里的残余气体
Whether there was a valve that failed to close, and they had to figure that out.
是否有个阀门失效了 没法关闭 所以他们必须要弄清楚这一点
But it burned for whoa, yeah, it burned well past the end of the official SpaceX stream.
但是 它烧了很久 在SpaceX官方直播结束后还在烧
And there was a lot of people anxiously wondering whether it was going to go the same way as SN10.
而有很多人焦急地想知道它是否会变得像SN10一样
There was this little fire suppression thing there, just trying to spray water on it,
那里有一个小小的只是试图向它喷水的灭火装置
but boy there was only so much it could do.
但老哥啊 它能做的只有这么多
But eventually, yeah, they shut the fire down.
但最终 是的 他们把火灭掉了
It's not and then actually they got out to look at the thing with the vehicle on the pad.
并没有爆炸 然后实际上在飞船还停在着陆场时 他们去那里看了看
They had people out there working on it.
同时人们也在那里进行一些工作
A few hours later, which was way faster than previous flights
这一切仅仅发生在着陆后几个小时 这比以前的飞行快多了
if you remember Hopper or SN5 or 6.
如果你记得星跳者或SN5或SN6
They had to wait like a day before the propellent had evaporated.
他们不得不在推进剂蒸发之前等了一天
So that they could safely send people out to this.
这样才敢安全地把人送过来
I'm not sure if they come up with a new way to safely depressurize it or something else.
我不确定他们是否研究出了一种新方法来安全地减压或者有其他什么措施
I know that they had robotic dog Spot
我知道 他们有机器狗Spot
that could walk around with sensors to verify that the environment was good.
可以带着传感器走来走去 核实环境是否良好
Yeah they've already got their tankzilla headed out to the pad to pick that up
是的 履带吊车去着陆场准备把它吊起来了
and presuming that they might either stick on a truck and bring it back or they might stick on a test stand.
而我认为之后可能会把它放在一辆卡车或者一个试验台上
I think, most likely, those will take it back to the hanger to the tall bay.
而且最有可能的是会把它带回高湾厂房(High Bay)
So that they maybe dissect to verify what's working, what's damaged。
这样 他们也许会拆开一些部件 来核实一些部件的状况 有没有损坏
Take a look at the state of the legs.
看一看着陆腿的状态
They might even take those Raptors out of there
甚至可能把这些猛禽从中拿出
and send them off to Mcgregor for inspection and more test firings.
并把它们送到麦格雷戈进行检查和更多的试车
That would seem like a fair thing to do,
这样做似乎是合理的
and so the next one that is going to fly is probably SN16,
那么下一个要飞的可能是SN16
which is nearing completion as we speak.
就在我们说话时 它已接近完成
We are told to expect that within a couple of weeks by sources who are not public.
而据不公开的消息来源说 预计将在几周内完成
Now this does come at an interesting time,
那么这确实是一个有趣的时间
because yes, a few weeks ago, NASA selected SpaceX's Starship
因为是的 几周前 NASA选择了SpaceX的星船
to provide human landing system for the surface of the moon, right for the Artemis program.
作为阿尔忒弥斯计划的载人登月系统
And this was a big deal.
而这是一件大事
The first of all, SpaceX has got in there, despite being very different.
首先 SpaceX已经参与了竞标 尽管与其他竞争者非常不同
And they somehow, I don't know, I didn't expect them to be a winner, right.
而且他们以某种方式 同时我得说我没想到他们会成为赢家 对吧
I didn't think that they were exactly the thing that NASA wanted,
我不认为星船是NASA正好想要的东西
I thought they might make an excellent second choice.
我认为他们可能是一个很好的第二选择
I never expected them to be the first choice,
我从来没有想到他们会成为第一选择
but NASA went with them.
但NASA还是选择了他们
And the biggest part of why they would go with them was because they were half the price of Blue Origin,
而这其中最大的原因是他们的价格是蓝色起源的一半
and we all know that they were half the price of Blue Origin,
而我们之所以知道这点
because Blue Origin submitted a protest, saying you didn't give us fair consideration.
是因为蓝色起源 提交了一份抗议书 说你们没有给我们公平的考虑
You didn't have a give us a chance to renegotiate our price.
你们没有给我们一个重新谈判价格的机会
I'm saying Blue Origin. That's not fair.
蓝色起源这个说法是不公平的
It's the national team, which is Blue Origin, Lockheed, Northrop Grumman and Draper.
其实是国家队 也就是蓝色起源 洛克希德 诺斯罗普·格鲁曼和德雷珀
So it's a fairly some old space people and one new space person.
那么 这差不多是一些老太空企业和一个新太空企业
And similarly, Dynetics published another protest,
而同样 Dynetics公司也发表了另一份抗议书
and we know that they were more expensive as well than the national team.
而我们知道 他们比国家队的方案更贵
And of course NASA because it had these protests in hand,
当然 NASA因为有这些抗议在手
they were legally required to stop their collaboration with SpaceX advancing on that project.
在法律上被要求停止他们与SpaceX在该项目上的合作进展
And SpaceX reacted by saying
而SpaceX的反应是
Okay, we're doing this anyway, like SpaceX has its own agenda.
好吧 不管怎样我们都要做这个 就像是SpaceX有自己的时间表
They're gonna let the human landing system contract do whatever it needs to do.
他们会让载人着陆系统合同做它需要做的任何事情
Maybe like if they come back and and they do get it, that'll be great.
可能像是如果之后他们回来还是拿到了合同 那就很好
I don't think at this point that there will be a change to SpaceX getting a human landing system award.
现在我不认为 SpaceX获得的载人着陆系统合同还会有变化
I do think that a big part of this protest and discussion that it's going to engender or drive
我确实认为 这种抗议和讨论的很大一部分 会引起或推动
will basically result in politicians say,
基本上会导致政治家说
hmm, maybe we need some more funding for this Artemis program thing.
恩 也许我们需要更多的资金用于这个阿尔忒弥斯计划的事情
I think that might be what happens.
我认为这是可能发生的事情
I mean, it's also entirely possible that both the other two or one of the other two,
我是指 也完全有可能是其他两家或者两家中的一家
accept some short term funding from some part of money the NASA confined
会从NASA的某部分有限的资金中获得一些短期的资金
with the hopes that the Congress will approve
同时希望国会能批准
a much more serious amount of money for the the actual human landing system for Atemis
实际上给阿尔忒弥斯的载人着陆系统提供更多的 大量的资金
because right now they basically they don't get what they need.
因为基本上现在他们没有满足资金需求
So yeah, what else is worth talking about?
那么 是的 还有什么值得谈论的呢？
Well, interestingly enough, the tiles are on the side.
恩 有趣的是 隔热瓦还贴在侧面
They had a fairly large section, in a smaller section.
贴成一大片和一小片区域
They actually lost a couple of tiles during test fires.
他们实际上在测试点火时丢失了几片隔热瓦
But it looks like if they lost any, they weren't particularly obvious during the the actual flight.
但看起来 在实际飞行过程中 可能没有丢失隔热瓦
Test fires might actually be a slightly more dangerous environment
测试点火实际上可能是一个稍微更危险的环境
because it's spending more time on the pad as opposed to in flight,
因为相比于飞行中 它花了更多的时间在发射台上
and of course you get reflection of sound and waves from the ground
而当然你会得到来自地面的声波的反射
that can really make for a very hostile sonic vibration environment.
而这真的可以产生一个非常恶劣的声波振动环境
By the way, a lot people have been asking
顺便说一下 很多人一直在问
why there are tiles being tested on the back of the fins,
为什么在翼面的背面有隔热瓦进行测试？
because the plan is to have the front of the vehicle that will go through re-entry to have their tiles,
因为计划是让飞行器的正面通过再入大气层时存在隔热瓦保护
and for the labored side to have nothing, just to have the silver shiny finish of the stainless steel
而背风面应该没有任何东西 只有银色闪亮的不锈钢表面
to reflect the incidental thermal radiation back into space.
来反射次要的热辐射到太空中
And so people will assume that that might be true of the fins.
那么 人们可能会认为翼面也是如此
However, the fins are in a slightly different situation,
然而 翼面的情况略有不同
first of all, they're actuating it to different angles.
首先 他们正以不同的角度来驱动它
And they may actually end up getting heat reflected from the body,
而且它们实际上可能最终得到来自机身的热量反射
but also just because you've got this sort of high pressure air being pushed around,
但也正是因为其被这种高压空气推来推去
it's entirely possible, you might have more heating on the back of the fins.
也完全有可能会在翼面的背面经受更多的热量
And finally, the fins are relatively thin, compared to the body,
而最后 与机身相比 翼面相对较薄
so there's a lot less thermal mass there.
所以那里的热质量要小得多
Therefore, they might actually need to have thermal protection on the back of all the fins
因此 实际上他们可能需要在所有的翼面的背面都加上热保护措施
to get them through re-entry.
以使其扛过大气层再入
I don't know. Somebody's probably modeled this in a lot more detail,
我不知道 有人可能已经对这个问题进行了更详细的建模
but since they're putting the tiles there, I expect they're considering this as a possibility.
但既然他们把隔热瓦放在那里 我想他们会考虑这种可能性
The Raptor engine plumes looked much more consistent than previous flights.
相比以前的飞行 猛禽发动机的尾流看起来要稳定得多
Usually we'd have one that was slightly orange,
通常情况下 会看到有一台的颜色略微有点发黄
and we'd be thinking, oh, that's a little bit about fuel rich.
而我们会想 哦 那是有点富燃的燃气
But there were much, much closer.
但是这次各台发动机之间的颜色却非常接近
Although there were definitely moments where they were running with off nominal mixtures,
虽然有些时候 肯定在使用非额定的混合比
probably for thrust reasons.
可能是节流的原因
So congratulations to SpaceX and everyone involved in Starship.
因此 祝贺SpaceX和参与星船的每个人
This has been great to watch, not just the development, the failures, the successes
这个项目一直很值得观察 不仅是开发 失败和成功的过程
and this first big step showing that it actually can work,
而且这样巨大的第一步也表明 它确实可以工作
and I hope that when SN16 flies that it similarly continues this tradition.
同时我希望 在SN16飞行时 它同样可以继续这一传统
And we can actually demonstrate that the level of reliability needed to make Starship work is achievable.
而且我们可以实际验证 使星船工作所需的可靠性水平是可以实现的
But yes, that will be in the future, we'll see SN16 fly in a couple of weeks,
但是 是的 这将是在(遥远的)未来 (而几周后)我们将看到SN16飞行
and of course I'll be watching.
当然我也会关注
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全